We're continuing our videos on particle
physics. In the last video, we showed
the derivation and solutions of the
Klein Gordon equation for scalar fields.
In this video, I'll go over the
derivation and solutions of the proca
and Maxwell equations for vector fields.
And in the next video, I'll do the same
thing for durac spinner fields.
So in field theory, our main inspiration
for vector fields is going to be the
Maxwell equations, which describe the
behavior of the electric field E and the
magnetic field B. These tell us that
electric fields diverge or converge
around electric charges and that
magnetic fields curl around electric
currents. These also tell us that
timevarying electric fields can generate
magnetic fields and vice versa.
Now the two Maxwell equations with
charge or current sources are called the
inhomogeneous Maxwell equations and it's
possible to derive these from a
lrangeian density.
To see this we'll have to spend a bit of
time discussing the properties of the
Maxwell equations.
First this equation tells us that the B
field doesn't diverge or converge which
means B can only curl. This means we can
write B as the curl of another vector
field which I denote as lowercase A.
This is the magnetic vector potential.
Now if we take the second Maxwell
equation and plug this in for B, we can
swap the order of the time derivative
and the curl. Since the curl is made of
space derivatives and the order of
derivatives doesn't matter, we can group
the curl terms on one side. Since the
curl of this expression is zero, this
vector field only diverges or converges.
So it can be written as the gradient of
a scalar field which is the electric
potential phi. Solving for E, we get
this equation.
So we have these two equations relating
the E and B fields to the potentials fi
and a. Writing out the XYZ components,
we get these six equations.
Now, it turns out that we can combine
the electric and magnetic potentials
into a space-time four vector capital A
where the time component is the electric
potential divided by the speed of light
C. We can also lower the index of A
using the manovsky metric which adds
negative signs to the space components.
So with the equations for the electric
field, we'll divide both sides by the
speed of light C. It should now be clear
that we can replace all the potential
terms with the components of the four
potential capital A.
Now each of these equations has the same
form, a difference of potential
derivatives involving two space-time
indices.
For example, this first formula involves
the indices Y and Z. And this formula
involves the indices time and x.
We'll now label these six formulas as
the components of a new tensor f with
the two relevant space-time indices as
subscripts.
This is called the Faraday tensor. In
matrix form, the Faraday tensor looks
like this.
An important property is to notice that
f is anti-ymmetric
which means the matrix transpose is
equal to its negative.
Another way of saying this is that
swapping the two tensor indices gives us
a negative sign.
Now this is the farad tensor with lower
indices. But we can also write it with
upper indices using two summations with
the manovsky metric.
In matrix form, the left metric gives
negative signs to these rows and the
right metric gives negative signs to
these columns. In the end, the B terms
get two negative signs, so their signs
are unchanged. But the E terms each get
one negative sign, so their signs are
flipped.
Now, let's look at the two Maxwell
equations with sources. Again, it's a
fact that the product of the epsilon and
mu constants is 1 over the speed of
light squared. And that lets us rewrite
these equations like this.
If we expand these equations using their
vector components, we can see the
equations can be rewritten in matrix
form.
And using Einstein summation notation,
this tells us that the partial
derivative summed with the Faraday
tensor gives us the four current capital
J times a constant.
So this is a compact form of the
inhomogeneous Maxwell equations and it
turns out that these Maxwell equations
can be derived from the following
lrangeian density.
Now with scalar fields we had this
version of the oiler lrangege equations
but since the four potential vector a
has four components we get four
different versions of the oiler lrangee
equations one for each space-time index.
However we're going to manage all of
them at once using a generic space-time
index new.
And recall for the lrronian density we
treat all field components and their
derivatives as independent variables.
So to put this lrangeian through the
oiler lrange equations we can start by
taking the derivative with respect to a
subalpha.
Here the derivative terms go to zero and
only the source term with j is left. J
does not depend on a so it can be
removed from the derivative.
Now when we have a partial derivative
involving two a components this equals
one if the components match and goes to
zero if the components are different
since they are independent.
So this gives us a chronicer delta which
gives one if the indices match and zero
if they are different.
Now the chronicer delta is basically
like an identity matrix that doesn't
change the results of a formula. it just
has the effect of replacing one of the
indices.
So this is one side of the Oiler Lrange
equation.
On the other side, we have the
derivative with respect to partial A.
The source term goes away and we're left
with the Faraday term for which we use
product rule.
Now for the derivative of f, we have two
derivative terms here. Here we have
space-time indices on the derivatives as
well as indices on the A's. These terms
will only be non zero if both the
derivative indices match and the A
indices match. So we get two chronicer
deltas here with both index types.
When we sum this with f and do all the
index replacements, we get f beta alpha
minus f alpha beta.
Remember since f is anti-ymmetric we can
swap the indices to get a negative sign
and this gives us 2f.
For the second term there's a little
more index gymnastics involved with
raising and lowering indices using the
metric but we also get 2 f as a result
giving 4 f in total.
So overall the oiler lrange equations
give us this
cancelling and rearranging gives us the
Maxwell equations we had earlier.
So we've indeed shown that this
lrangeian gives us the correct Maxwell
equations.
Now since the electromagnetic field is
massless, this lrangeian does not have a
mass term. But we could generalize this
lronian to include massive fields by
adding a mass term here that is
quadratic in the field a. This is
similar to the mass term in the Klein
Gordon equation that was quadratic in
phi. This generalization is called the
proca lrangeian
and the resulting equation of motion is
the proa equation which has a mass term.
For the rest of this video I'm going to
look at the solutions of the proca
equation where the mass is non zero but
the source term is set to zero. This
describes massive vector particles like
the w and zed bzons involved in the weak
force.
I'll return to the massless Maxwell
version of this field as a special case
later in the video.
So let's begin solving the proca
equation.
Now the proca equation is more
complicated than the Klein Gordon
equation since the vector field A has
more components.
However, our work solving the Klein
Gordon equation has already helped us
find solutions to the proca equation. To
see why, we'll do a few algebraic
tricks.
Let's take the proca equation and take
the derivative with respect to new on
both terms.
Now the f tensor has the property of
being anti-ymmetric.
This means that if we swap the two
indices, the result is the same but with
a negative sign in front. Meanwhile,
these two derivative operators form a
symmetric tensor. Meaning that if we
swap the indices, the result is the same
with the same sign. This is because the
order of partial derivatives doesn't
matter in calculus.
Now, it's a theorem that when we have a
symmetric tensor that is completely
summed with an anti-ymmetric tensor, the
result is always zero.
This is because every term in the
summation will always get canceled out
by another term with the opposite sign.
If you like, you can think of this as
saying that multiplying a symmetric
matrix and an anti-ymmetric matrix
together and taking the trace will
always give zero.
So if we know this summation goes to
zero, we're left with this property here
for the vector a which is called the
lorren condition.
Now this lorren condition tells us
something important. Although A has four
components, if we know three of them,
then the fourth component is
automatically determined by the other
three. This means that there are really
only three degrees of freedom for A, not
four. This fact will become important
later.
If we go back to the ProAka equation and
write out the definition of f and
distribute the derivative, this term now
goes to zero because of the Lorren
condition.
The result is this formula here which is
the Klein Gordon equation.
This tells us that each of the four
components of the A vector individually
satisfy the Klein Gordon equation.
This is good news because instead of
having to solve for the four component
functions individually, we can simply
pick one syosoidal function for all four
components and then write down a column
of four constant scaling components for
the four space-time directions.
All that's left is to determine the four
constant components of this vector,
which I'm going to label using alphas.
Now before we start solving for these
alphas, I'm going to review some
notation.
Remember capital A is a vector field
which is a solution to the proca
equation. And we're looking for
solutions with this form of a single
cosine wave with a vector of four
constant alpha amplitudes for the four
space-time directions.
To make this more concise, we can write
alpha with a generic mu index which
represents one of the four space-time
indices.
And once again, we can write out a
cosine wave as a complex exponential. If
we remember the cosine solution is just
the real part of this complex wave.
It's also common to write the frequency
omega over c as the time component of
the wave vector k superscript t. Here
I've also written the four spac-time
variables time xyz using x's with time
xyz superscripts.
It's also common to write the four
space-time indices using numbers where 0
indicates time and 1 2 3 indicates the
spatial xyz directions.
It's also possible to lower the indices
on k to make them subscripts. If we
remember to flip the signs on the xyz
components,
remember lowering the indices of a
vector is done with the manovsky metric
which has minus signs for the xyz
directions.
Finally, we can write the sum formula
between the k's and x's using an
implicit Einstein summation over new.
So our proca solutions for the vector
field capital a take this form and we
need to solve for the four alpha
constants.
We can solve for them using the lorren
condition we saw before where we take a
derivative summed with a and set it to
zero. Since the alphas are constant the
derivative can pass by them and just act
on the complex exponential.
Now if we were to consider the case
where this was a time derivative which
is a derivative with respect to x0 the
derivative would only care about the
time term in this exponential
and so we get a chain rule term of i k
sub0 out in front.
More generally this derivative in the mu
direction will give us a chain rule
factor of i * k sub mu out in front. And
since the Lorent condition says this is
all equal to zero, we can cancel the
complex exponential and get this
relationship between alpha and k.
So the lorren condition basically tells
us that the wave vector k and the
scaling amplitude vector alpha must have
an inner product of zero.
Now to simplify this formula, we're
going to take the special case of a wave
traveling in the z direction.
So the x and y components of the wave
vector k are zero and only the time and
zed components are non zero.
This means the four components of the
wave vector k look like this.
So from the Lorren condition we showed
that the wave vector K and the amplitude
vector alpha must have an inner product
of zero.
We can also write this as the row of K
components multiplied by the column of
alpha components equaling 0.
Or we could write out the sum explicitly
like this.
Now using the simplified assumption of
the wave traveling in the Z direction,
kx and ky go to zero. So the formula
simplifies to this.
Now in this sum, the k's have lower
indices and the alphas have upper
indices. To make things easier, I'm
going to raise the indices of k using
the manovsky metric.
This doesn't change KT, but raising the
index of KZ changes its sign.
So our formula now looks like this.
And we need to find alpha vectors that
solve it.
One simple solution for the alphas is to
set alpha x to one and set all other
alphas to zero. As a vector, this
solution looks like this.
Another solution is to set alphay to one
and set all other alphas to zero which
looks like this.
The third and final solution is to set
alpha x and alpha y to zero and set
alpha t to k zed and set alphaz to kt
as a vector. This solution looks like
this.
Now you might think that kt and kzed are
independent values here. But if we
recall the dispersion relation for Klein
Gordon waves, the value of KT here is
completely specified by KZ and the
field's mass. So choosing KZ fully
specifies this vector.
We now have three solutions to the proca
equation for a wave traveling in the Z
direction.
And since the zed direction is
arbitrary, this means the proca equation
always has three basic solutions for a
given wave vector direction.
So for the Klein Gordon equation, once
we selected the components of our wave
vector K, there was exactly one solution
up to a scaling constant.
However, for the proca equation, after
we've selected the components for our
wave vector K, we actually get three
different solutions which have the same
wave direction and frequency, but
different constant vectors in front.
These constant vectors give different
polarizations for the wave. Let's take a
closer look at these polarization
vectors.
In the first solution, we see the wave
oscillates back and forth along the x
direction as a vector. We call this
horizontal polarization.
In the second solution, the wave
oscillates back and forth along the y
direction as a vector. We'll call this
vertical polarization.
In the third solution, the wave
oscillates back and forth along the Z
direction as a vector, which is along
the axis of wave propagation.
We'll call this longitudinal
polarization.
Now, let's forget about the special case
of a wave traveling in the Z direction.
More generally for any given wave vector
K there will always be two proca
solutions which oscillate perpendicular
to the direction of wave travel. These
are called transverse solutions.
And there is also the third proca
solution which is longitudinal
polarization
which oscillates in the direction of
wave travel.
Now you might see the two transverse
polarizations rewritten in different
ways.
For example, way back in video three, I
showed that we can combine the
horizontal and vertical polarizations in
different amounts and different phase
delays to get other types of
polarizations such as left and right
circular polarizations.
So you might see these three basic
polarizations written as left circular,
longitudinal and right circular. These
are also called spin 1, spin 0 and spin
minus1 polarizations.
Okay. So we understand that with the
proca equation if we choose a wave
vector k we get three basic solutions.
But an important observation is that the
proca equation is linear just like the
klein gordon equation. So the sum of any
two proca solutions gives us another
proa solution.
So to get the most general solution to
the proca equation, we do the following.
We start with one basic syosoidal
solution with a wave vector K. Just like
the Klein Gordon equation, this wave
vector must obey the dispersion
relation. This means that given the XYZ
wave numbers, the time component of K,
which is the frequency, is already
determined by the field's mass.
Now we can add any number of sinosoids
together to get another solution. So we
can do an integral over all possible
wave numbers kx k y k z and give each
one its own complex amplitude curly a
that depends on the wave vector.
This complex number includes both
amplitude and phase information.
And finally each basic wave can appear
in one of the three polarization vectors
which I'm denoting as epsilons 1 2 and
three. So we must also include a
summation over r from 1 to 3 for the
polarizations.
The amplitude curly a for a given wave
should depend on both the wave vector k
and the polarization r. If we take the
real part of this, this is the most
general solution to the real proca
equation.
The next thing I'll do in this video is
discuss the solutions to the Maxwell
equations, which is a special case of
the proca equation where the mass is
zero. This seems like a small change,
but the massive and massless solutions
to the proca equation do have some
important differences.
First, since the proca equation is
massive, the dispersion relation tells
us that the phase velocity of each basic
wave solution is different depending on
the wave vector. But for the massless
solutions, all wave solutions travel at
the same speed of light C regardless of
the wave vector.
The biggest difference between the
massive and massless cases is that the
massive case has three possible
polarization solutions whereas the
massless case only has two transverse
polarization solutions and there is no
longitudinal polarization.
To see why this happens, let's discuss
gauge transformations.
Now with our potential formula for the
electric field in the special case of
electrostatics the time derivative part
goes to zero and the E field can be
written as the gradient of a scalar
function phi. This leads to a special
property where if we transform the
potential phi by adding a constant value
k everywhere then when we take the
gradient of the transformed version the
gradient of a constant k goes to zero.
So the result is unchanged.
This means that the electric field E is
completely unchanged by this potential
transformation in the special case of
electrostatics.
This means that there are multiple
possible phi potentials that give the
same electric field and the same
physics.
In the full electronamics case, we've
rewritten the E and B fields as the
Faraday tensor F shown here.
Now let's transform the four potential a
by adding the gradient of a scalar
function partial mu lambda.
Now if we take our faraday formula and
transform a this way after we distribute
the derivatives the lambda derivatives
cancel and the formula remains
unchanged.
So here we see that the F field is
completely unchanged by this
transformation of A and there are
multiple possible A potentials that lead
to the same F field and the same
physics. We call these type of field
transformations that leave the physics
unchanged gauge transformations.
And the specific choice of a potential
is called a gauge.
Now I want to take a moment to talk
about the different types of
transformations we can do in physics.
Let's say we do some type of physics
experiment with electricity and
magnetism and record the results. The
next day we rotate the experiment setup
90° and do the same experiment. We would
expect to get the same result. This is
because the laws of physics in our
universe do not depend on spatial
direction. In other words, the laws of
physics have rotational symmetry.
In terms of the mathematics, we can see
rotational symmetry in a given lronian
density if we rotate all the vectors and
tensors in the lrangeian density by 90°
and see that the lrronian density is
unchanged.
This means that the action s which is
the integral of the lrangeian density is
also unchanged.
So the principle of stationary action
will give equivalent results.
Now we recently discovered a type of
transformation on our electromagnetic
for potential A which leaves the Faraday
tensor F unchanged and therefore leaves
the Maxwell arrange density and its
action S unchanged.
You might think that this is pretty
similar to our example of rotating our
experiment setup. However, there is an
important difference between the two.
When we rotate our experiment 90°, we're
actually changing the physical state of
the experiment, which we can measure
using physical coordinate axes.
But when we gauge transform our four
potential A, we're not changing the
physical state of the experiment. This
is because the four potential A is not
directly measurable. Only the
electromagnetic field F is directly
measurable.
So when we gauge transform A, we're not
changing the physical state. We're just
changing to another mathematical
description of the same physical state.
And that's what we mean by gauge
transformation.
It's a change in mathematical
description for the same physical state.
Now let's see what happens when we take
the procoian and apply this gauge
transformation.
We've shown that when we do this
transformation on A, the F tensors are
left unchanged.
But the mass term contains A's that will
get transformed.
If we distribute all this out, we see
that we keep the mass term, but we get
three extra terms added onto the
lrangeian.
So this transformation changes the
lrangeian and would change the physics
we observe for the field.
However, if we set the mass term to
zero, it disappears and we get the
Maxwell Lrangeian.
Since a gauge transformation leaves F
unchanged, this means the Maxwell
Lrangeian is completely unchanged by a
gauge transformation
and the physics of the field will stay
the same.
Now, here we've left out the Maxwell
source term. But even if we include the
source term and gauge transform it, we
can use product rule here and this first
term goes to zero as long as the current
J obeys a continuity equation.
And this second term is a divergence
term which means it will go to zero when
we integrate the langian density to get
the action S. So even if the lronian is
changed here, the action S is not. So
the physics is unchanged.
So this is a fundamental difference
between the proca and Maxwell
lrangeians.
With the Maxwell lrangeian we can do
these gauge transformations on the field
a and still get the same physics. But
this is not true for the proa case.
This is a subtle but important
difference between the proca and maxwell
fields.
For example, we saw that with proa
fields, the Lorren condition is a
mandatory property. But for Maxwell
fields, the Lorren condition is not
automatically true. Instead, we can do a
gauge transformation on A to make the
Lorent condition true by using a clever
choice of lambda in our gauge
transformation.
This freedom to gauge transform a
without changing the physical situation
is the reason that longitudinal
polarizations no longer appear for
Maxwell fields. Let's see why. We'll
start with a longitudinal wave traveling
in the Z direction. So the wave co-
vector K looks like this where only the
time and zed components are non zero.
And for the longitudinal polarization,
the field vector itself only has time
and zed components. So it points along
the direction of wave travel.
Because Maxwell waves are massless, the
dispersion relation tells us that the
time and zed components of the wave
vector must be equal up to a difference
in sign. We'll choose the plus sign and
set kz equal to kt in both the
exponential wave and the polarization
column vector.
Now let's do a gauge transformation on
a. We'll use a field lambda that looks
like a plane wave times the imaginary i.
In our gauge transformation formula,
this derivative here represents four
spac-time derivatives that we can
arrange in a column.
Now one inconvenience here is that the
derivatives have upper indices. We can
lower the indices if we remember to flip
the signs on the xyz components using
the manovsky metric.
Now the time derivative brings down i kt
and the z derivative brings down
negative i kt meaning these two negative
signs cancel and the x and y derivatives
give zero.
Now the time and zed components each
have a pair of complex i's and
multiplying them gives us negative 1's.
Finally subtracting these two terms
gives us the zero vector.
So what we've shown here is that
anything that looks like a longitudinal
wave is actually equivalent to the field
equaling zero everywhere because the two
field configurations are linked by a
gauge transformation that does not
change the physics of the situation.
Both gauge choices lead to the same
electromagnetic field.
So for our massless Maxwell field, the
fact that there are multiple gauge
fields A that lead to the same physical
situation means that longitudinal
polarizations in the vacuum do not
exist. Only transverse polarizations
exist.
This is why electromagnetic waves in the
vacuum only have transverse
polarizations and no longitudinal
polarization.
As an aside, something similar happens
in the case of gravitons, which are spin
2 particles.
Massive spin 2 particles normally have
five polarizations.
But for the massless case, like
gravitons, only the plus2 and minus2
polarizations exist, which are
equivalent to the plus and cross
polarizations for gravitational waves.
You can check out my videos on
gravitational waves if you want to learn
more.
The last thing I'll cover in this video
is the notion of vector particles and
antiparticles.
This will largely be a repeat of the
explanation of antiparticles in my Klein
Gordon video. So if this explanation
goes too fast, you can review that
video.
So with the Klein Gordon field we found
that if we made the scalar field fi
complex and wrote this lrangeian with
phi star five product terms we actually
doubled the number of solutions. We
found taking the oiler lrange equations
and varying with respect to phi star
gave us a fi klein gordon equation with
particle solutions and varying with
respect to phi gave us a phi star klein
gordon equation with antiarticle
solutions.
We also saw the u1 symmetry of the
lrronian led to a conserved current by
not theorem and this was the
electromagnetic current.
The exact same thing happens if we take
a look at the complex version of the
proca field by including complex
conjugate terms in the lrangeian.
Taking the oiler lrange equations and
varying with respect to a star gives us
the a proa equation for particles
and varying with respect to a gives us
the aar proca equation for
antiparticles.
This lrangeian also obeys a U1 symmetry.
So if we give every A a positive phase
and every A star a negative phase, they
all cancel out leaving the lrangeian
unchanged.
This leads to this conserved current
here, which again is the electromagnetic
current.
So when it comes to real proca fields,
these are for vector particles that are
their own antiparticle and have zero
electric charge. This describes the
photon which has zero mass and the z
bzon involved in the weak interaction.
Complex proca fields are for vector
particles where the particle and
antiparticle fields are distinct and the
particles do have electric charge. The
main example here is the W bzons where
the W plus and W minus Bzons are
particle antiparticle pairs described
together by a complex field.
Now keep in mind these lrangeians are
for free particles with no particle
interactions. The langians would get
much more complicated if we included
particle interaction terms.